<chapter xml:id="interface">
<title>User interface</title>

<para>
You navigate through the UI in dfterm2 by using arrow keys and ALT+number keys (or ESC+number keys). Dfterm2 has a simple windowed interface. Windows are automatically arranged and will not overlap unless you are short on terminal screen space. 
</para>

<para>
Currently focused window has a blue border. Other windows have gray border. If the currently focused window is also locked, the border is red.
</para>

<para>
You can use CTRL+F to enlarge currently focused window to fullscreen and CTRL+L to lock a window. Locking can be particularly useful in game window where some of the keys used by dfterm2 might conflict with the keys the game uses.
</para>

<para>
CTRL+R can be used to remove the borders of currently focused window.
</para>

<para>
CTRL+X is used to hide a window. You can unhide the window by pressing CTRL+X again while focused on it. This is useful if, for example, you don't use the chat dfterm2 provides. You can press CTRL+X when focused on chat window and it goes away.
</para>

<para>
There is a chat in dfterm2 you can access after logging in. In chat, you just type in your message and press enter. You can navigate old chat history by using arrow keys or pgup/pgdown.
</para>

<simplesect>
<title>Remapping keys for the interface</title>

<para>It is possible to change the keys used for the interface. This is one of the few things in dfterm2 that are configured by modifying a configuration file.</para>
<para>There are some limitations in remapping the keys. The keys cannot be remapped per user. In other words, the keymapping configuration will be the same for everyone connecting to your server.</para>
<para>Another limitation is that the interface windows still say "Alt+1", "Alt+2" etc. in their titles, even though these may be mapped to something completely different.</para>
<para>Finally, know that some characters cannot be transmitted through a terminal. Most notably, shift+arrow keys or shift+return don't work. You may need some trial and error to see what works and what doesn't.
</para>
<para>The keymapping configuration file is called <emphasis>interface_keymappings.conf</emphasis>. You can edit this with any text editor, such as Windows' notepad. Instructions on modifying this file is in the file itself.
</para>
</simplesect>

</chapter>

